P: Presumably, not everyone is convinced by this research?
J: No. The book hasn’t been well received by the free-range parent community,
who argue that any kind of intensive parenting ruins family life.
They say it harms children’s happiness and doesn’t produce particularly successful or creative offspring.
P: Yes, they tend to think children are hugely over-supervised these days,
that they don’t have time to think for themselves and just expect to be entertained…
J: Yes, but the authors of the book say that the evidence doesn’t really support that.
They argue that it’s about finding a balance.
The really clever part about helicopter parenting
when it’s done well is that these parents use what social scientists call ‘soft power’.
They are aiming to shape children’s values and preferences so
that the children appear to be making those choices of their own accord.
So, their children tend to acquire a good work ethic and resilience when they are faced with challenges
– and these are valuable personal characteristics that will have an effect on their future success.
There’s also a Swedish study which says that these children are less susceptible to depression,
better at concentrating, and generally more self-confident.
P: Does the book imply, then, that this is the best parenting system
regardless of what country you’re from or what the education system is?
J: No, and this is, in a way, the most interesting argument.
The authors don’t say that there is only one possible parenting style.
What they explain is that parenting styles are a reflection of the economic situation
in a particular country at a certain time.
So, in countries where there is considerable economic inequality,
such as the UK or the US at the moment,
there are more parents who push their children to succeed from a young age,
because there’s so much to be gained by doing well in life.
However, in the UK in the 1970s,
when there was less difference between the lives of the most and least successful,
parenting styles were generally more relaxed, which was appropriate at that time.
And, today, if you look at countries where the average income is higher
and they have less economic inequality, such as Sweden and Finland, again,
parenting can still be more relaxed because there’s not so much to lose by not being a high achiever.
And, typically, children in Scandinavia and the Netherlands tend to be far less competitive,
and qualities such as creativity and independence are more highly prized,
because that’s what they need to succeed.
P: So, what kind of parents are the authors? Do they say in the book?
J: Both authors say they’re almost certainly helicopter parents, but,
as I was saying, they don’t think that this is the only ‘right’ parenting style.
P: Just that it produces the best outcomes in unequal societies?
J: Yes, that’s right.
And they highlight the importance of having the right parenting style for your circumstances.
For example, being an over-controlling parent – a tiger parent
– may produce great exam grades, but these children,
often those from countries where there is a huge focus on academic achievement,
have the most mental health problems, along with low levels of creativity.
These children never have the opportunity to develop their natural talents,
and it can make them stressed and unhappy in the short term.
And, with free-range parenting,
children may develop their creative side and learn to make their own decisions,
but they may also make the wrong decisions,
or miss opportunities because their parents aren’t involved enough.
P: Well, how fascinating, and how difficult to get that balance right.
If you want to read more, the book we’ve been discussing today is Love, Money, and Parenting:
How Economics Explains the Way We Raise Our Kids,
by Matthias Doepke and Fabrizio Zilibotti, published by Princeton University Press.
Thank you very much, Janice, for talking to us today…
So, what kind of parent are you? I have to say I’m totally free-range…